School of Criminology fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
School of Criminology fonds
1972 - 1985
F-7
38 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
School of Criminology
The School of Criminology was established under the name of the Department of Criminology by the Board of Governors in February 1975. In 1984, it was renamed the School of Criminology. The School is responsible, through its Director, for the promotion of research and the development and delivery of programs in the field of Criminology. The first director, Dr. Ezzat Fattah, set out the goals of the Criminology program, which included the mission to contribute to public education and public enlightenment about crime and justice through the dissemination of scientific, unbiased information; accelerate the shaping of a fair, rational and responsive criminal justice system; promote understanding and co-operation between people in the social, legal and behavioral sciences, in and outside the University, through an interdisciplinary and integrative approach, through team teaching and team research, and; contribute in various ways to social development and social reform.
In December 1972, a faculty ad hoc committee recommended that graduate and undergraduate programs in Criminology be established and incorporated within the Division of General Studies. In August 1973, the Senate resolved to accept this recommendation. In 1974, Criminology was established as a program within the new Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, before becoming a full department the next year. In 1985, the School left the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies to become a departmental unit within the Faculty of Arts.
In 1978 the School added an M.A. program to its offerings, followed in 1984 by the addition of a Ph.D. program. In meeting its research and instruction mandates, the School has sponsored the Criminology Research Centre, whose management committee consists of members of the department. The School has also taken part in the University's Directed Independent Study Course (DISC) Program, recruiting its first Distance Education Coordinator in 1979 and offering its first DIS course in 1980. In May 1981, The Universities Council of B.C. approved the establishment of Certificate Programs (General and Advanced) in Criminology, comprised of a variety of home study courses. The School also sponsors conferences on various topics, and members of the department have attended conferences elsewhere.
The School has been organized administratively into a Director, Associate Directors, and a number of standing committees. The Director is the chief administrative officer, whose responsibilities include the management of the operational budget; faculty tenure, promotion and salary recommendations; teaching assignments; and representation of the School to external bodies. The Director reported, until 1985, directly to the Dean of Interdisciplinary Studies. The Associate Directors have been responsible for space allotment, the appointment of sessional staff, the coordination of curriculum development in graduate and undergraduate programs, and advice to the Director on specific matters. The Departmental Assistant is responsible for much of the day-to-day administration of the School, including the management of the departmental budget, the scheduling of courses, the provision of liaison with administrative offices, and advising students.
The number and composition of departmental committees has varied over time. Long-standing committees include the Undergraduate and Graduate Curriculum Committees. The School also struck various ad hoc committees when required, including those on Field Practices, Planning and Co-ordinating; Statistics; and Legal Studies.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds of the School of Criminology consists of records created and received in the course of the administration of the School and the carrying out of its functions of providing instruction and promoting research. The activities documented include policy and procedures development; the planning, initiation and administration of curriculum and programs; departmental and faculty meetings; and the publication of brochures and reports. The types of documents include meeting agenda and minutes, correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets and reports.
The fonds was arranged and originally described by the archivist in 1990. The arrangement and titles of series by subject were provided by the archivist.
Verdun-Jones, Simon N.; Chappell, Duncan; Fattah, Ezzat A.
The records were transferred in a number of accessions from the School since the early 1980s.
Additional material has been accessioned but not yet processed (1.67 m., 1981-1987). Consult with the archivist about unprocessed accruals. Further accruals from the department are expected.
Consult the inventory to the Faculty of Arts fonds, F-2. Also consult the inventory to the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies fonds, F-23.
Some access restrictions apply in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the appropriate series level description and the archivist.
File lists are available.
- Departmental History, 1972 - 1974; F-7-1; 4 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the history of the School, including proposals for the establishment of the Criminology program and a departmental history. It includes reports.
  - Proposals for undergraduate curriculum, 1974; F-7-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Correspondence, 1972; F-7-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Papers: department history - proposal for criminology program, 1972; F-7-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
- Correspondence, 1975 - 1979; F-7-2; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence and related materials received and sent by the School Director. It includes brochures, memoranda, questionnaires, and annual and other reports. Names that appear in file titles as correspondents or subjects are listed below under Access Points.
  Teaching Support Staff Union
  Access to records in the series is restricted in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the unit list and the archivist for further information.
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1975; F-7-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1976; F-7-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1976; F-7-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1977; F-7-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1977; F-7-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1978; F-7-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 7-1)
  - Chronological correspondence - Chair, 1978; F-7-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Chairperson's correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-7-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Chair's correspondence - TSSU, 1979; F-7-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Employee appraisal, 1978; F-7-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Student appraisal, 1978; F-7-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Correspondence - general, 1977 - 1978; F-7-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
- Departmental committees, 1976 - 1978; F-7-3; 6 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the records of various departmental committees. It incudes circulars, correspondence, agenda and minutes of meetings, and memoranda.
  - Departmental meetings, 1976 - 1977; F-7-3-1; 1 cm of textual records
    - Agendas, minutes and papers, 1976 - 1977; F-7-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Undergraduate curriculum committee, 1976 - 1978; F-7-3-2; 2 cm of textual records
    - Agendas, minutes, and papers, 1976 - 1978; F-7-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
    - Field school proposals, 1977 - 1978; F-7-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
    - Transfer credit, 1978; F-7-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Graduate curriculum committee, 1978; F-7-3-3; 1 cm of textual records
    - Agendas, minutes, and papers, 1978; F-7-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Field practices, planning and coordinating committee, 1977 - 1978; F-7-3-4; 1 cm of textual records
    - Agendas, minutes, and papers, 1977 - 1978; F-7-3-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Statistics committee, 1976; F-7-3-5; 1 cm of textual records
    - Agendas, minutes, and papers, 1976; F-7-3-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Legal studies committee, 1978; F-7-3-6; 1 cm of textual records
    - Legal studies, 1978; F-7-3-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
- Faculty committees, 1974 - 1980; F-7-4; 1 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the records relating to committees of the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, including the Curriculum Committee. It includes correspondence, course proposals, and memoranda.
  Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies. Undergraduate Curriculum Committee
  - Course proposals and papers, 1974 - 1978; F-7-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Course proposals and papers, 1979 - 1980; F-7-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
- University committees, 1977; F-7-5; 1 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the records relating to University committees, including the University Review committee. It includes memoranda and reports.
  University Review Committee
  - University Review Committee, 1977; F-7-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
  - Agendas, minutes, and papers (Missing as of Sept. 12, 1997), 1977; F-7-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-2)
- Field school, 1976 - 1978; F-7-6; 2 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the operation of the Field School, including student placement and seminars. It includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports.
  Access to records relating to student placements is restricted in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the unit list and the archivist for further information.
  - General correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-7-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Student placements, 1977 - 1978; F-7-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Analysis, 1976 - 1977; F-7-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Field practice manual, 1977 - 1978; F-7-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
    Open
  - Seminars, 1978; F-7-6-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
- Subject files, 1975 - 1979; F-7-7; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to various subjects, including the B.C. Police College, distance education, the Isaac Ray Memorial Lectures, and Law Foundation grants. It includes correspondence, memoranda, reports and statistics. Names that appears in file titles as correspondents or subjects are listed below under Access Points.
  British Columbia Police College; Canadian Police College; Law Foundation of British Columbia; University of Ottawa; Criminology Student Union
  - British Columbia Police College, 1975; F-7-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Canadian Police College, 1979; F-7-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Clarkson's prison reform proposal, 1979; F-7-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Committee list, 1978; F-7-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Courses in statistics and/or research design, 1977; F-7-7-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Student Union constitution and correspondence, 1975 - 1978; F-7-7-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Distance education, 1977 - 1978; F-7-7-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Distinguished criminologist series, 1975 - 1978; F-7-7-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Extended studies diploma program, 1977; F-7-7-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Filing system, general office, 1976; F-7-7-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - The Isaac Ray Memorial lectures, 1978; F-7-7-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Law Foundation library grant, 1977 - 1978; F-7-7-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Law Foundation research grant, 1978; F-7-7-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Retreats (departmental), 1978; F-7-7-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Series on juvenile crime, 1977; F-7-7-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Statistics course, 1978; F-7-7-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - University of Ottawa, external review, 1977; F-7-7-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
- Conferences, 1979 - 1980; F-7-8; 2 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to various conferences sponsored, or attended by, members of the Department. It includes agenda, correspondence, pamphlets, and reports.
  - Female offenders workshop, 1979; F-7-8-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Incarcerated offenders workshop, remedies, not problems, 1979; F-7-8-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Managing the criminal justice system, 1980; F-7-8-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Conference correspondence, 1979 - 1980; F-7-8-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
- Publications, 1980 - 1985; F-7-9; 1 cm of textual records
  Series consists of various publications of the School promoting its programs. It includes brochures, pamphlets, and reports.
  - Criminology brochure, 1984; F-7-9-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
  - Assorted publications, 1980 - 1985; F-7-9-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 7-3)
- Student Issues, 1977; F-7-10
  Series consists of records relating to students, including grade change requests by individual students.
  Access to records in this series is restricted in accordance with Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy legislation. Consult the unit list and the archivist for further information.
  - Grade change requests, 1977; F-7-10-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 7-3)